Finding Aid for Walter I. McKenzie Papers 1914-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter I. McKenzie Papers
1914-1962
1918-1919
1946-1947
McKenzie, Walter I. (Walter Ingles), 1888-1962.
Detroit attorney, assistant U. S. Prosecutor at the International Military Tribunal for the Far East following World War II; correspondence and official court materials largely relating to Japanese intervention in Manchuria; materials relating to service in Polar Expedition to northern Russian during World War I; miscellaneous papers relating to other political and legal activities; and photographs.
2009195 Aa 2 UAm
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Walter McKenzie family (Donor no. 6495 ) and came to the library in 1980-1981.
The collection is open for research.
Walter Ingles McKenzie was born in Muskegon, Michigan February 9, 1888. He graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1915. During World War I, he served as a member of the 339th Infantry sent to northern Russia as part of the Polar Bear Expedition; and during the 1920s and 1930s he was a Democratic party worker and candidate for state office.
In 1946, Walter McKenzie was granted a leave of absence from his position as Referee in Bankruptcy for the Eastern District of Michigan to serve as an Assistant U.S. Prosecutor at the International Military Tribunal for the Far East. As part of the so-called Japanese War Crimes Trial, McKenzie was specifically charged with that part of the indictment relating to Japanese military aggressions in Manchuria. McKenzie stayed in Tokyo for much of 1946, then returned to the United States in 1947, where he resumed the practice of law.
The Walter McKenzie Collection consists largely of materials created as a result of the Japanese War Crimes Trials. The collection has been arranged into eight series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Articles, Speeches, etc.; International Military Tribunal for the Far East, International Prosecution Section; University of Michigan; World War I (Polar Bear Expedition); Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
International Military Tribunal for the Far East.; Japan.; McKenzie, Walter I. (Walter Ingles), 1888-1962.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Detroit (Mich.); International Military Tribunal for the Far East.; Japan.; McKenzie, Walter I. (Walter Ingles), 1888-1962.; McKenzie family.; Military art and science.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Personal clippings (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes letters to family and friends largely concerning McKenzie's activities in Japan with the military tribunal.
  - Dated files, undated; 1914-1937; 1944-1958; 15 folders (Box 1)
  - Exchanges with wife and other family members, March-November 1946; 7 folders (Box 1)
- Articles, Speeches, etc
  The Articles, Speeches, etc. series relates to the war crimes trials.
  - Articles by McKenzie re. Japanese War Crimes Trial (Box 1)
  - Speeches, speech notes, and announcement of speeches (Box 1)
- International Military Tribunal for the Far East. International Prosecution Section
  The largest series includes official court materials of the International Military Tribunal for the Far East. In this category, the researcher will find memoranda of the International Prosecution Section, materials prepared and presented in connection with the charge of Japanese aggression in Manchuria, and interrogations and affidavits of Japanese officials involved in high-level military decision-making. Of special interest is a series of monthly diaries for the period when McKenzie was stationed in Japan.
  - Charter of Tribunal; rules of procedure (Box 1)
  - Regulations and memoranda re. mechanics of trial, personnel assignments, etc (Box 1)
  - Memoranda re. document processing, analysis, and translation (Box 1)
  - Indictment (Box 1)
  - Jurisdiction of tribunal (motions and briefs) (Box 1)
  - Opening statement of prosecution (Joseph B. Keenan) (Box 1)
  - Opening statement (drafts and background material) (Box 1)
  - Memorandum: "The Crime of Conspiracy" by Brendan F. Brown (Box 1)
  - Manchuria (section of indictment relating to Japanese aggression in Manchuria)
    - Opening statement of John Darsey (Box 1)
    - Background reports, memoranda, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Outline of proof (Box 1)
    - Evidence (additional documents) (Box 1)
    - Brief (rough notes) (Box 1)
    - Brief book (Box 1)
    - Trial brief (Box 2)
    - Summary of proof (Box 2)
    - Evidence, notes, etc., 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Lytton Report synopsis (Box 2)
    - John Powell affidavit (Box 2)
    - Waiver of Rule 6b-1 (Box 2)
  - Interrogations and affidavits
    - Araki, Sadao (Box 2)
    - Ishihara, Kanji (Box 2)
    - Itagaki, Seishiro (Box 2)
    - Kamei, Kenichiro (Box 2)
    - Kasagi, Ryomei (Box 2)
    - Kido, Koichi (Box 2)
    - Machino, Takeuma (Box 2)
    - Mitsuchi, Chuzo (Box 2)
    - Morishima, Morito (Box 2)
    - Ogata, Tatekora (Box 2)
    - Okada, Keisuke (Box 2)
    - Shimizu, Konosuke (Box 2)
    - Tada, Hayao (Box 2)
    - Tanaka, Ryukichi (Box 2)
    - Tojo, Hideki (Box 2)
    - Wakatsugi (Baron) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Trial miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Telephone directories and lists (Box 2)
  - Japanese record of proceedings (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Personal financial and administrative miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Judgment, November 1948; 7 volumes (Box 2)
  - Monthly diaries, March-December 1946 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series is small and consists of notes from Law School classes and an accumulation of programs for sporting events and entertainments that he attended.
  - Law school notes and examinations, circa 1914; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Programs to musical and sporting events (Box 3)
- World War I (Polar Bear Expedition)
  The World War I series pertains to McKenzie's service as a member of the Polar Bear Expedition during the last months of the First World War. Largely photocopies of materials still in family possession, this series includes correspondence to family members and a diary of his experiences. There is also some original material in this series such as postcard views of Russia and an accumulation of pamphlets and newspaper clippings. Also included are a group photo of the 339th Infantry taken July 14, 1919 at Camp Devens, reunion photos and portraits of McKenzie and others.
  - Introductory Materials, 4 items (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Diary of experiences in Russia, 1918-1919; 1 items; 127 pages (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January 1918-July 1919
    - January-June 1918, 7 items (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - July 1918, 30 items (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - August-September, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - October-December 1918, 31 items (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - January-March, 1919, 19 items (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - April-May, 1919, 20 items (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - June-July, 1919, 15 items (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Polar Bear Association Reunion Programs, 6 items (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, 7 items (Box 3, Folder 11)
      (Includes announcements of Polar Bear Association events)
    - Miscellaneous
      (Includes a copy of Vol. 1 No. 1 of The Mess Kit a humorous publication for "the Soldiers of the A.E.F."; an issue of The Call, a broadsheet of "the workers and peasants of Russia, to their English speaking fellow workers"; several issues of the Daily Communique; duty rosters; pamphlets; notes and personal items.)
      - [Bentley Library material], 22 items (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - [Loaned Material], 17 items (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings, 6 items (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photocopies of other clippings, 41 items (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Post-cards of Russia, 33 items (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Polar Bear Photographs
    - Portraits of McKenzie, Draftees Marching, and Miscellaneous, 7 items (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Reunion group photos and Miscellaneous, 7 items (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Souvenir Folders
      (Commercially produced packets of photos)
      - Life in the U.S. Army, Camp Mills (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - New York City, Night Views (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Group photos, 339th Infantry, Camp Devens July 14, 1919 and Reunion photos, 1921-1945, 6 items (Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous contains a mixture of political, professional, and personal materials. This series contains the best documentation of McKenzie's activities as an attorney outside of his war tribunal responsibilities.
  - Political miscellanea, 1920s-1930s (Box 3)
  - Legal materials (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous opinions (referee in bankruptcy), 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Personal cash book, 1924-1928 (Box 3)
  - Printed Material (Box 3)
    (Includes journal of the National Association of Referees in Bankruptcy, Michigan Supreme Court decisions, and Detroit Red Cross disaster preparedness plan)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
    (largely concerning political and charitable activities)
- Photographs
  (also in oversize folder UAm)
  The Photographs series includes portraits and family photos; photos of the 339th U.S. Infantry during the 1918-1919 intervention in northern Russia; photos of Veterans of Foreign War activities in Detroit; and photos of the International Military Tribunal and other activities in Japan.
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Family and miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Far East War Crimes Trial, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Other Japanese subjects (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan (Box 3)